Finding aid for the American Association of University Professors (AAUP)- Xavier University Chapter Records
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
American Association of University Professors (AAUP)- Xavier University Chapter Records
1961-2011
1961-1987
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
American Association of University Professors. Xavier University Chapter
.8 linear feet (2 manuscript boxes)
These records, dating between 1961-2011, were generated by the Xavier University Chapter of the American Association of University Professors (AAUP). They document faculty participation in the chapter and activities pertaining to faculty salaries, university budget issues, and campus communication.
XUA-92
History of American Association of University Professors (AAUP)- Xavier University Chapter
The American Association of University Professors (AAUP) is a professional organization devoted to representing college and university faculty members. The Xavier University Chapter of the AAUP was established sometime in late 1962, and remained active until around 1986. It joined the Ohio Conference of the AAUP in 1965. The chapter addressed issues concerning faculty benefits and salaries, tenure and rank requirements, university budget issues, and relationships among departments, faculty, administration, and students. The chapter actively researched collective bargaining options in the 1970s and early 1980s and engaged in discussions about the university's acquisition of Edgecliff College during the same time. On March 16, 2009, a group of faculty members restored the chapter and it remained active for several years thereafter. At the time of the writing of this finding aid (2017), University Archives is unaware of a formal dissolution of the chapter although there is no evidence of its continuance.
Scope and Content
The records are organized into two series and date from 1961-2011. Series I, which dates from 1961-2011, contains constitutions, minutes, correspondence, and research files generated by the Xavier University Chapter of the AAUP. Series II, which dates from 1964-1982, contains correspondence, reports, newsletters, and publications generated by the Ohio Conference of the AAUP and the National Office of the AAUP.
Statement of Arrangement
The records are organized into two series: Series I, American Association of University Professors (AAUP)- Xavier University Chapter Records and Series II, American Association of University Professors (AAUP)- Ohio Conference and National Office Materials.
Restrictions on Access
Materials in this collection are available for patron research, but may only be used in the University Archives room by appointment.
Acquisition Information
Original acquisition date and method unknown.
Accruals
Accrual of 2009-2011 chapter records received by Thomas Kennealy, University Archivist, from Nancy Bertaux in 2011.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Collective bargaining -- College employees -- Ohio.
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio) -- Faculty.; American Association of University Professors. Xavier University Chapter
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Series I: American Association of University Professors (AAUP)- Xavier University Chapter Records, 1961-2011
  Series I contains constitutions, minutes, correspondence, surveys, and reports created by the Xavier University chapter of the AAUP. Topics addressed in the minutes and correspondence include faculty salaries and benefits, chapter officer elections, campus communication, academic freedom, student enrollment, and Xavier University's relationship with the Jesuit community. Material from the late 1970s through the early 1980s discusses Xavier University's acquisition of Edgecliff College. There are also research files on topics such as collective bargaining, institutional mergers, and affirmative action. In addition, the series contains by-laws, minutes, and correspondence from the restoration of the chapter from 2009-2011.
  - Constitutions, 1962-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1962-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    Includes correspondence between the Xavier University Chapter, chapters at other universities, the Ohio Conference, and the National Office.
  - Motions for consideration, 1985 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    The motions address the financial state of Xavier University and faculty participation in the budget process.
  - Collective bargaining research files, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Articles about institutional mergers and affirmative action, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Faculty salary surveys, 1961-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series II: American Association of University Professors (AAUP)- Ohio Conference and National Office Materials, 1964-1982
  Series II consists of correspondence between the chapter and the Ohio Conference of the AAUP and the AAUP National Office as well as reports, newsletters, and publications dating from 1964-1982.
  - Ohio Conference minutes, directories, and reports, 1964-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Ohio Conference newsletters, 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National Office correspondence and newsletters, 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Office membership kit, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)